Finding Aid for Michigan Theater Foundation records, 1981-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Theater Foundation records 1981-2002, 1984-1998
Michigan Theater Foundation.
(in 6 boxes)
4.5 linear feet
2011096 Aa 2
Michigan Theater Foundation was formed in 1979 when it purchased the Michigan Theater in Ann Arbor, Mich., a historic landmark built in 1928 and restored by the fundrasing efforts of the Foundation. The record group comprises administrative records, including files of the Executive Director, Board of Trustees and administrative committees; grant proposals, materials related to fundraising, theater restoration, renovation, and membership campaigns; descriptions of programs, series, and individual events taken place at the theater; publicity photographs, audio- and video (VHS) recordings, and outsize posters and calendars of events.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by Michigan Theater Foundation (donor no. 10558 ) in May 2011; subsequent additions have been made.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Theater, currently listed on the National Register of Historic Places opened its doors in January 1928. The architect, Maurice H. Finkel of Detroit, designed it for both live stage and film performances. Angelo Poulos, a local businessman constructed the shell of the theater and the adjoining office building, W.S. Butterfield Company which operated several motion picture and vaudeville theater in Ann Arbor and throughout Michigan, supervised the construction and furnishing of the theater's interior. An eleven-piece orchestra accompanied the live stage acts, while the silent movie shows were accompanied by the Barton Pipe Organ. In 1929 the orchestra and vaudeville presentations were disbanded as the Michigan Theater switched to an all-talking film format, but the Barton Organ was played into the 1940s. On occasion during the 1930's, 40's, and '50s touring Broadway shows played live-on-stage and included such stars as Helen Hayes, Ethel Barrymore, Paul Robeson, Uta Hagen, Jose Ferrer, Zasu Pitts, and Bela Lugosi.
As television started to replace the movies as the public's first choice for popular entertainment, the management took an attempt to "modernize" the theater in 1956. Unfortunately, the original architectural design of the façade and outer lobby were destroyed, and stylistically inappropriate fixtures replaced the original chandeliers and wall sconces.
In the 1960s-1970s the theater became less and less profitable to operate, and the Butterfield Theater Corporation decided not to renew their lease and the theater was put up for sale. A number of area volunteers joined the forces to buy the Ann Arbor landmark. In early 1979, the theater was sold to their newly-formed Michigan Theater Foundation, a non-for-profit corporation dedicated to preserving the facility. The theater reopened in September 1979.
To secure the financial future of the Michigan Theater, a millage tax designed to pay off the theater's mortgage and make $200,000 worth of code improvements was placed on the April 1982 election ballot. The citizens of Ann Arbor showed their support for the arts in their community by volunteering to increase taxes to support this project.
In the summer of 1982 an architectural firm was hired to create a restoration plan for the theater. An anonymous challenge gift of $500,000 was pledged in the fall of 1983. In 1985 the Michigan Theater embarked on a $1.5 million fundraising campaign to restore the theater to its 1920's glory. In 1986 the State of Michigan granted $125,000 to the Michigan Theater as part of the State Equity Funding Program. The restoration of the Michigan Theater continued from May through September 1986 and reopened the same year. A new screening room addition was added in 1999 along with additional restrooms and office space.
The Michigan Theater Foundation Board of Trustees hired Russell B. Collins to head a professional management team that sought to bring audiences back to the Michigan Theater. The Board and new management revived the tradition of bringing live-on-stage touring theater. The Michigan Theater provided stage for touring Broadway shows throughout the 1980s. The Ann Arbor Symphony made the Michigan its primary concert hall starting in 1984. Composers, musical performers, dance and drama companies, comedians, and performers in other genres from around the world have been making appearances at the theater since the mid-1980s. By 1989 the Michigan Theater had gained a reputation as one of the nation's most successful presenters of contemporary performing arts. During the period reflected in the present collection, the Theater developed Not Just for Kids! series of live shows and films perfect for the entire family and Serious Fun at the Michigan series of musical and theatrical performances.
Over 100,000 people yearly experience film classics, documentaries, the best of the world cinema, and films by independent American film-makers. The Michigan Theater Foundation has made a special commitment to revive the art of silent era film by presenting silent films with live music.
The records date to the period of the Michigan Theater Foundation's intensive fundraising campaign to preserve the Michigan Theater and the first 15 years of its life after the theater reopened its doors in 1986.
Subjects:
Michigan Theater (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Michigan Theater Foundation.; Fund raising--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Historic buildings--Conservation and restoration--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Motion picture theaters--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Organ (Musical instrument)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Performances--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects: Visual Materials
Michigan Theater (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Motion pictures.; Motion picture theaters--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Organs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Performance arts--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors
Collins, Russell B.
Genre Terms:
Audiocassettes.; Negatives.; Performing arts posters.; Photographs.; Posters.; Promotional materials.; Publicity photographs.; Slides (photographs); Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series contains files of the Executive Director, the Board of Trustees, administrative committees, by-laws, budgets, financial reports and statements, strategic planning documentation; materials related to the Michigan Theater restoration: surveys, reports, and plans; materials related to membership campaigns, volunteer recruitment, and staff newsletters. Also included articles and interview notes taken by Russell Collins on the subject of history of Ann Arbor's three theater venues --Hill's Opera House, the Whitney Theater, and Michigan Theater; programs and newspaper advertisements of performances at the Ann Arbor theaters; and Collins' article on the subject of history of American musical theater.
  - History
    - American Theater, by Russ Collins (Box 1)
    - Hill's Opera House, Ann Arbor (Box 1)
    - Whitney Theater, Ann Arbor (Box 1)
    - Michigan Theater, Ann Arbor (Box 1)
  - By-laws 1989, 1993 undated (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees 1984-1996 with gaps (Box 1)
  - Director 1980s (Box 1)
  - Executive Director 1997-1998, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Board Nominating Committee 1992-1994 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee 1989-1996 with gaps, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Development Committee 1988-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Facility Committee 1991-1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Fundraising Committee 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - Operational Support Committee 1993-1996 (Box 1)
  - Awards 1987-1991 (Box 1)
  - Budgets 1981-1991, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Financial reports 1980-1997 with gaps, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Membership 1989-1998 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1987-1988, 1994-1996 (Box 1)
  - Restoration-Phase I 1982 (Box 2)
  - Restoration-Phase II 1984-1986 (Box 2)
  - Restoration publicity 1988-2001 (Box 2)
  - Special projects 1980s-1990s (Box 2)
  - State Street Area Association 1995 (Box 2)
  - Strategic planning 1987-1992 (Box 2)
  - Volunteers 1991-1995 (Box 2)
  - "Wolverine" Theater: Internal Analysis and Design, 1995 (Box 2)
- Development
  The Development series contains grant proposals, descriptions of programs, and letters of support accompanying Michigan Theater's grant applications for federal, state, and private funding. Also included here are materials regarding awards received by the Michigan Theater, correspondence with individual and corporate sponsors and fundraising organizations, information about private and corporate giving; records related to specific fundraising needs, events and campaigns led by the theater, correspondence regarding donations in kind made by the Michigan Theater to local groups and organizations; correspondence regarding donations in kind made by the Michigan Theater to local groups and organizations.
  - Grants
    - Ann Arbor Community Foundation 1988-1994, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Arts Midwest 1987-1995 (Box 2)
    - Kresge Foundation 1984 (Box 2)
    - Mervyn's grants 1983-1995 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Association of Community Arts Agencies 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Council for the Arts 1990, 1992, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Council for Arts and Cultural Affairs 1993-1996, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Equity Grant 1988-1990, 1992, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - National Endowment for the Arts 1984, 1987/1988-1994/1995 with gaps, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Touring Arts Program 1995 (Box 3)
  - Fundraising
    - Arts in Education Project 1990 (Box 3)
    - Capital Fund Drive
      - Feasibility study September 1983 (Box 3)
      - Committee meetings 1984-1985 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence and memoranda 1980-1985, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Corporate sponsors 1988-1995, 2000-2002, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Crisis Campaign 1991 (Box 3)
    - Direct mail campaigns 1989-1991, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Donations in kind 1987-1996, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Donor survey 1990 (Box 3)
    - Fundraising events 1983, 1988-1996, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Huron Valley Fundraisers Network 1990-1995 (Box 3)
    - Large gifts 1989-1997 with gaps (Box 3)
    - Needs 1987-1991 (Box 3)
- Repertoire
  The Repertoire series includes correspondence, schedules, agreements and publicity materials (flyers, programs, and photographs) related to specific programs shown at the theater in the 1980s-1990s (e.g., Dizzy Gillespie, Meredith Monk, Mel Tormé, among others), as well as materials related to general program development.
  - Shows and performers 1987-1989, 1995, 2003, 15 folders (Box 4)
  - Program development 1980s-1990s (Box 4)
  - Publicity
    - Printed programs 1980s-2000s, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Flyers 1980s-2000s (Box 4)
  - Youth programs 1991-2003 (Box 4)
- Visual materials
  The Visual series includes photographs, negatives and slides, and two video cassettes in VHS format. Photographs, slides and negatives are divided into two major categories: Michigan Theater and Publicity. The Michigan Theater visual materials include images of the Theater, mostly after the restoration; photographs of Michigan leadership and staff, photographs taken during events and performances that took place at the theater; slides advertising local businesses and/or containing information about donors that were demonstrated before performances and during events. Among publicity images are studio photographs and slides advertising films and live performances at the Michigan Theater.
  One of the two VHS cassettes contains advertisement of the 1000 Airplanes on the Roof performance at the Michigan Theater. The second VHS cassette contains a Canadian Broadcasting Corporation promotional video of Mikado at the Stratford Festival of Canada.
  - Photographs
    - Michigan Theater 1980s-1990s, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Publicity photos, A-Z and miscellaneous, 13 folders (Box 4)
  - Negatives
    - Michigan Theater images (Box 5)
    - Publicity images (Box 5)
  - Slides
    - Michigan Theater 1990s-2000s (Box 5)
    - Publicity, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - VHS tapes
    - 1000 Airplanes on the Roof advertisement (Box 5)
    - Mikado, Stratford Festival of Canada promotional tape (Box 5)
- Audio materials
  The Audio series contains recordings of radio advertisements of shows and Michigan Theater promotional advertisement, as well as a recording of As Time Goes By performed by an unidentified female vocalist accompanied by the Barton Organ.
  - Audio cassettes
    - As Time Goes By performance (vocal, the Barton Organ), undated (Box 5)
    - A Christmas Carol promotional recording, undated (Box 5)
    - Michigan Theater promotional recording June 10, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Philip Glass performance promotional recording undated (Box 5)
  - Audio tapes
    - Broadway bound promotional recording, September 14, 1987 (Box 5)
- Outsize materials
  The Outsize series contains issues of the monthly Michigan Theater calendar and oversize posters and flyers used by the Theater to advertise performances.
  - Michigan Theater calendar, 1994-1999 with gaps (Box 6)
  - Publicity posters 1980s-1990s (Box 6)